你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到PWN学院
welcome to pwn college
我是Yan，在这个视频中，我们要讨论的是
I'm Yan and in this video we're going to talk about
内存损坏的原因
the causes of memory corruptions
这是内存错误模块的下一集视频
this is the next video in our memory errors module
根据我们有多少时间来讨论三到四个原因
will cover three or four causes depending on how much time we have
如果需要的话，我们会把它分成两个视频
if we need to we'll cut this into two videos but we'll see what happens
我们来看看
so we're gonna go through
几个非常常见的导致记忆损坏的原因
a couple of very common causes of memory corruption
这个列表并不详尽
this is list isn't exhaustive
事实上，确实有缺失的原因，我们将在后面的模块中讨论
and in fact there are definite missing causes that we will cover in later modules
让我们开始吧
but let's roll
好吧
all right
让我们从经典的缓冲区溢出开始
let's start with our classic buffer overflow
这是我在上一模块中讨论过的
this is what I discussed in the last module
不好意思，不是在上一模块
all right sorry not in the last module
是在上个视频中
in the last video
这很简单
it's just very simple
缓冲区有大小
you have a buffer it has a size
你在缓冲区中写入了太多的数据
and you write too much data into that buffer
覆盖了它，从而攻击栈
and you override it and clobber the stack
嗯
um
这种情况经常发生，因为
this happens a depressing amount and it happens because
C语言不隐式跟踪对象的大小
C does not implicitly track sizes of objects
如果你想要注意大小，你必须
if you want to be careful about sizes you have to
非常小心地在代码中添加校验
have checks all over your code to be extremely careful
我们很容易忘记做这些校验
and it's very very easy to forget these checks
我这里有一个最小的缓冲区溢出的例子
right so here I have the smallest possible example I think of a buffer overflow
它在栈上有一个小缓冲区，16字节
which basically just has a small buffer on the stack of 16 bytes
我们用128字节的数据来溢出它
and we just overflow it with 128 bytes of data
很简单
nice and simple
这个程序绝对是有问题的
there's no world in which this program isn't buggy
让我们来看看发生了什么
let's take a look at what happened
好的，第一个我会过一遍完整利用流程
alright and the 1st one I'm going to run through full exploitation
最终达到赢的目的
and to end all the way through to a kind of a win condition
我们将（在下一模块）讨论代码注入等作为内存破坏利用的一部分
we'll talk about shell code injection and so forth as part of memory corruption exploits
在下一模块，把所有东西都拼起来
in the next module  actually in putting everything together
但是现在让我们看一下这个最小的例子
but let's take a look at this minimal example for now
我直接添加了这个win函数
I just added this win function
这是我们在溢出后重定向到的函数
and this is where we will redirect code execution after our overflow
好的，让我们再编译一次
alright let's compile this again
在这个视频中，我编译时会关闭栈保护
for this video I'm compiling everything without what is called stack Protection
这个模块后期会学习什么是栈保护
later this module you learn what stack Protection is
我们来编译一下
so let's compile it
关闭栈保护器
all right so no stack protector
好，很容易
nice and and easy here
我还会禁用位置无关的可执行文件(PIE)
I'm also gonna disable position independent executable
这样我们就知道所有的地址在哪里
so that we know where all the addresses are
为了演示的目的，简化了攻击流程
will just make it very simple for the purposes of this demo
我们会编译buffer_overflow.c(演示程序)
and we'll compile buffer overflow that seems to buffer overflow
好了，我们有了缓冲区溢出演示程序
alright so we have our buffer overflow
如果我运行它，并给它很长的输入
if I run it and I give it a whole lot of input
它会崩溃
it will crash
如果我想看看在哪里崩溃的
well actually if I see where it crashed
我可以看内核日志
I look at my kernel log
可以看到它在这里崩溃了
and I see that it crashed here
如果我去反汇编
if I do disassemble
看看崩溃点在哪里
and see where that point was
它就在这里，在返回时崩溃了
it was right here it crashed at the return
在函数返回时，崩溃了
at the return we have a crash
我们执行了缓冲区溢出
we perform a buffer overflow
我们利用了缓冲区溢出，这导致程序在返回时崩溃
we exploit a buffer overflow vulnerability and that caused the program to crash at the return
让我们更详细地看看发生了什么
let's see what happened in a little bit more detail
如果我们在GDB中运行它
if we run this in GDB
执行了它
we run it of course
它让我们输入一些东西，我们输一堆a
it asks us for some input and we put in a bunch of A's
砰，它崩溃了
boom it crashed
那就是它崩溃的地方
that's where it crashed
正如右边（ppt上）预期的那样
as expected on the right
当然
and of course
ret指令从栈上弹出返回地址
return pops the return address off the stack
让我们看看栈上有什么。都是A
let's see what's on the stack all A's
所以栈上有一个缓冲区
so there's a buffer on the stack
我们用大量A溢出了它
we overflowed it with all A's
现在返回地址是AAAAAAAA
now there's excuse me the return address is all A's
这是个坏消息
and it's bad news okay
让我们利用这一点，当然这是我们的目标
let's exploit this right our goal of course
既然我们控制了返回地址
since we control the return address and
在程序返回时
the program is returning
我们可以去到任何我们想去的地方
we can return anywhere we want
这个函数是个很好的目标
and this function is nice enough
这个程序是很好利用的
this program is nice in the sense that
因为我们加入了这个win函数
we have compiled this win function
如果我们调用win函数，如果我们返回到win函数
if we call the win function if we just return here
我们会得到目标flag
we'll get our flag
当然这里我做了个假flag来演示
and I created of course a little fake flag for us to leak
win函数在4011af
alright the win function is at 4011af
太棒了
that's pretty awesome
那么我们该如何利用内存破坏漏洞呢
so how do we do this for memory corruption exploits
我强烈建议您使用pwntools
I highly recommend that you use pwntools
一般情况下请使用pwntools
in general please use pwntools
如果你在这门课上到目前为止一直没用pwntools
if you've been getting away without pwntools so far this course
现在开始是切换到pwntools的时候了
this is probably the time to switch
让我们用python写一个程序
so let's write a program that in python
会和这个有漏洞的程序交互
that will interact with this vulnerable program
并执行攻击
and perform the attack
Pwntools有一些很棒的调试功能
pwntools has some awesome debugging capability
它集成了GDB
it has GDB integration
如果我们这样做启动我们的程序
if we do this to launch our program
启动的进程和使用pwn.process启动的完全一样
it'll act exactly as a normal process if you have done pwn.process
但它会启动一个调试器让我们与之交互
but it'll instead launch up a debugger for us to interact with
这很完美
so this is pretty perfect
我们有一个进程
we have a running process
而且这个进程是在GDB中运行的
but that running process is running in GDB
我们也可以访问GDB
and we also have access to oops to GDB
好，我们来看看大概是什么样子
all right so let's just see what this looks like
如果我们将A*128发送到这个进程
if we send to this process the letter A times 128 times
字节a，好了
byte a all right
如果我们继续，我们会看到它崩溃了
and if we just continue here we'll see that it crashed
不出所料，全是A
as expected all A's
问题是我们要发送多少个A
so the question is how many A's do we have to send
回想一下，缓冲区有16字节长
recall that buffer was 16 bytes long
让我再看一遍
let me take a look at it again
哇，这输出的二进制，哦不
wow that's the binary oh no
在这里
here it is
16字节后就是返回地址？
16 bytes long is the return address right after that
不是的。回想一下，栈上还有其他东西
well no.  recall there's other stuff on the stack
还有保存的基指针等等
there's the saved base pointer et cetera et cetera et cetera
所以这16字节之外的是什么？
so really what is somewhat farther than 16 bytes
有内存对齐用的填充
there's padding
有很多东西可以在那里
there's a lot of stuff that can be there
所以我们要算出要写多少个A
so we have to figure out how many A's to write
实际上，使用pwntools这非常简单
this is actually pretty easy with pwntools
Pwntools有一种叫做循环模式的东西
pwntools has something called a cyclic pattern
我们可以说给我一个128字节的循环模式
we can say give me a cyclic pattern of 128 bytes
在这个循环模式中任何4字节都可以
and with this pattern any 4B in this pattern we can
向pwntools查询这些4字节在循环模式中的位置
query pwntools and say where in the cyclic pattern are these 4B
它会告诉我们
and it will tell us
这就能准确地告诉我们
so this will tell us exactly
返回地址在我们的输入中的位置
how far into our input the return address gets over written
让我们重新启动，退出这个GDB
so let's restart it here let's quit out of this GDB
重启它
restart this guy
我们现在不发送这个了
and we will now instead of sending this
我们将发送128字节的循环模式
we will send the cyclic pattern of 1 28 bytes
我们继续
here let's continue
它崩溃了，让我们看看RSP上有什么
it crashed and let's see what is at RSP
你可以看到这是一些可打印的东西
okay you can see this is some other printable stuff
这就是我们的循环模式
this is our cyclic pattern
我们把它打印出来
let's just print it
这里是gaaa haaa iaaa
so here it's gaaa haaa iaaa
这些都是我们可以查询的循环模式值
this is all cyclic pattern values that we can look up
我们取这个gaaa
so let's take this gaaa
并查询pwntools
and query pwntools
我们可以调用cyclic_find
so we can do cyclic find
来找出gaaa在循环模式中的位置，即24
to find where gaaa is in the cyclic pattern and says 24
所以我们需要输入24字节
so we need to go 24 bytes in
或者说输入24字节后开始覆盖返回地址
or 24 bytes into our input is when we start overriding the return address
现在我们知道了。这很棒
so now we know this is great
现在让我们来测试一下
now let's test this out
让我们结束这个GDB
let's close out this GDB
再运行一次
run this again
现在当我们发送
and now when we send
让我们送
let's send
A*24
a times 24
加上B*8
plus B times eight
所以现在返回地址应该被B覆盖
so now we should override the return address with all Bs
这里继续
set continue here
没错，都是b
correct it's all Bs
好了，现在我们准备进行最后一步
okay now we're ready for the final step
让我们来看看
let's take a look
win函数在bufferoverflow演示程序的哪里
where in the buffer overflow the win function is
就在这里
it is right here
我也可以反汇编它
I could have also disassembled it and whatever but
这是4011af
here it is 4011af
当然，pwntools有一个很好的
and of course pwntools has a nice
函数来转换这个
function that will convert this
把一个数字
a number
转换成小端序或其他字节表示形式
into the byte representation in little endina or whatnot
反正要和你的目标内存中的字节序一致
that you're currently exploiting in memories
这就是它的样子
so that this is what this will look like
现在我们再次启动它
so now we launch it again
哦，我忘了退出另一个GDB
oh I forgot to log out the other GDB
好了，现在我们再次启动它
alright now we launch it again
我们不发送b，而是发送这个
let's instead of the the Bs we'll send that
好了继续
okay continue
现在我们崩溃了，但是在其它地方崩溃的
and we crash that we crash somewhere else now
我敢肯定是win执行后
so I will positive that what happened is that win ran
win返回时
and then win returned
win返回到某个非法位置，导致了崩溃
and then win return to some other crap that crashed
因为我们覆盖了栈上太多数据
because we over wrote too much stuff
让我们来看看
so let's take a look
我们可以用readall()读出所有的字节
we can just read all read out all the bytes
pwntools你在开玩笑吗
are you joking pwntools
哦，对，对，对，我们先退出GDB
oh right right right so let's log out a GDB
就在这里
and here it is
我们收到的字节是pwn_college
the bytes that we received were pwn college 30880
那是假flag
that's the fake flag
我只是创造了一个随机数
I I I created just a random number
好吧，现在我们有了这些，我们可以
all right um now that we have all of this we can just
创建了一个短的脚本
created a very short script
我们所要做的就是用pwn.process替换GDB debug
all we have to do is replace GDB debug with pwn.process
这将在GDB外启动进程
and this will relaunch things outside of GDB
然后我们执行readall()
and then we do that read all
回车，boom，我们的利用成功了
enter boom there's our exploit
太棒了，这就是栈缓冲区溢出
awesome so that is the stack buffer overflow
非常经典的例子
the very classic example
这节课就讲到这里
I'm actually going to end this video here
我们再做一个视频
and we'll do another video for
讲内存损坏的其余原因
the remaining causes of memory corruption
待会儿见
see you very soon